<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.8" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="adaptive" kind="page">
    <compoundname>adaptive</compoundname>
    <title>Adaptive bases</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>The EXP uses two production varieties of adaptive bases: <orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A spherical Sturm-Liouville (SL) basis conditioned on an input spherial profile: <ref refid="class_sphere" kindref="compound">Sphere</ref></para>
<para></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A cylindrical SL basis conditioned on an input disk profile using an empirical function method: <ref refid="class_cylinder" kindref="compound">Cylinder</ref></para>
<para></para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
<para>Each of these bases are constructed when instantiated from scratch or from a cache file written by a previous invocation. The spherical SL basis is quick to construct, so caching is overkill. The construction of the <ref refid="class_cylinder" kindref="compound">Cylinder</ref> case can take hours of wall clock time, so reusing the basis is often desired. As described in <ref refid="config" kindref="compound">Configuration files</ref>, each <ref refid="class_component" kindref="compound">Component</ref> has a short config file which specifies the <ref refid="class_pot_accel" kindref="compound">PotAccel</ref> class, the component parameters, the file containing the phase space and <ref refid="class_pot_accel" kindref="compound">PotAccel</ref> parameters. In particular for the <ref refid="class_cylinder" kindref="compound">Cylinder</ref> class, the parameter which specifies the cache file is <computeroutput>eof_file=.eof.cache.file</computeroutput> where <computeroutput>.eof.cache.file</computeroutput> is the name of the cache file for this case. The cache file is read and compared with the desired <ref refid="class_cylinder" kindref="compound">Cylinder</ref> class parameters, if they match, the cache file is used, otherwise, the basis is recomputed from scratch.</para>
<para>The fields for the intrinsically two-dimensional cylindrical basis functions can take many hours to compute on a single node/laptop. </para>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="adaptive.doc"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
